Guide to the David Brion Davis Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Additional materials, 1949-2016; Accession 2017-M-0002
  - Writings
    - Books and reviews by Davis
      - The Problem of Slavery in the Age of Emancipation
        - Chapter 5 colonization, slavery, prisons, et cetera, Circa 1950s-circa 2010s (Box 22, Folder 4)
        - Chapter 9 used material, Circa 1950s-circa 2010s (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - The Problem of Slavery in Western Culture, 1957–1972 (Box 22, Folder 6-7)
        Includes outlines, notes, correspondence, reviews, and award material for The Problem of Slavery in Western Culture.
      - The Problem of Slavery in the Age of Revolution, 1770-1883
        - Chapter 4 text and lecture use, Circa 1950s-circa 2010s (Box 23, Folder 1)
        - Michael Kammen notes, Circa 1950s-circa 2010s
          - Chapter 1, 1973 (Box 23, Folder 2)
          - Chapter 2, 1973 (Box 23, Folder 3)
          - Chapter 3, 1973 (Box 23, Folder 4)
          - Chapter 4, 1973 (Box 23, Folder 5)
          - Chapter 5, 1973 (Box 23, Folder 6)
          - Chapter 6, 1973 (Box 23, Folder 7)
          - Chapter 8, 1973 (Box 23, Folder 8)
        - Manuscript chapters with notes, Circa 1973 (Box 23, Folder 9)
        - Clippings and advertisements, 1975–1976 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - New World Slavery chapter 8, 2004 (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - Slavery and Human Progress correspondence, 1975–1983 (Box 24, Folder 3)
      - From Homicide to Slavery files, 1985–1993 (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - Revolutions: Reflections on American Equality and Foreign Liberations Harvard University Press files, 1989–2000 (Box 24, Folder 5)
      - Boisterous Sea of Liberty: A Documentary History of American from the Discovery through the Civil War files, 1998–2000 (Box 24, Folder 6-7)
      - Inhuman Bondage
        - Correspondence, 2004–2007 (Box 24, Folder 8)
        - Outlines and summaries, 1997–2005 (Box 24, Folder 9)
        - General notes, 2002-2005, undated (Box 24, Folder 10)
        - Chapter 1, Amistad New World Slavery, 2000–2003 (Box 25, Folder 1)
        - Chapter 2, The Ancient Foundations of Modern Slavery, 1986-2004, undated (Box 25, Folder 2-3)
        - Chapter 6, The Atlantic Slave System, 1600-1800, Circa 2000 (Box 25, Folder 4-5)
        - Chapter 7, Slavery in Colonial North America, Circa 2000 (Box 25, Folder 6-7)
        - Stanley L. Engerman notes, 2004–2005 (Box 25, Folder 8)
        - Abolitionism in America notes, mostly from Inhuman Bondage, 2006–2007 (Box 25, Folder 9)
        - Correspondence, 2008 (Box 25, Folder 10)
        - Acknowledgments and permissions, 2005, undated (Box 25, Folder 11-12)
      - Atlas of Transatlantic Slavery, 2006–2007 (Box 25, Folder 13)
      - Book on slavery for children, 2013–2014 (Box 25, Folder 14)
    - Articles by Davis
      - William & Mary Quarterly, Race introduction, 1996 (Box 25, Folder 15)
      - Family and boundaries paper and Rush lecture, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 26, Folder 1)
      - Impact of British abolitionism on American sectionalism leading to Civil War, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 26, Folder 2)
      - Idea of Progress paper, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - Unidentified articles, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence regarding articles, 2002–2006 (Box 26, Folder 5)
      - Feminine role and home and education writing on Freudianism, 1966 (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - Race articles, general, 1994 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Writing notes by Davis, miscellaneous
      - Filing, procedures, bibliography notebook databanks, 1985–1987 (Box 26, Folder 8)
      - Yale Art Gallery exhibit, Baule art and sculpture, Ivory Coast, 1997 December (Box 26, Folder 9)
      - Books, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 26, Folder 10)
      - Reviews, 1994 (Box 26, Folder 11)
      - Notes on unidentified writings, 1987-2005, undated (Box 26, Folder 12)
      - Notes on unidentified writings, 1987-2005, undated (Box 27, Folder 1-2)
      - Book 2, labor, 2003 (Box 27, Folder 3)
        Includes notes on an unidentified writing on labor.
    - Third party writings and notes
      - Slavery and antislavery, a bibliography of recent works in English, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 27, Folder 4)
      - Islands of History notes, 1993 (Box 27, Folder 5)
      - Slavery in Political Thought notes, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 6)
      - Patterson, Slavery and Social Death, 1982–2011 (Box 27, Folder 7)
      - Sheldon Meyer essay, 1999 September 30 (Box 27, Folder 8)
      - Eli Faber, Jews and the Slave Trade, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 27, Folder 9)
      - Jim Stewart, essays, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 27, Folder 10)
      - David R. Roediger, The Pursuit of Whiteness: Property, Terror, and Expansion, 1790-1860, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 27, Folder 11)
      - Lois H. Horton, From Class to Race: Gradual Emancipation and Northern Racial Reconstruction, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - Joanne Pope Melish, The "Condition" Debate and Racial Discourse in the Antebellum North, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - James P. Ronda, "We Have a Country": Race, Geography, and the Invention of Indian Territory, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - Jon Gjerde, "Here in America There is Neither King nor Tyrant": European Encounters with Race, "Freedom," and Their European Pasts, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - Daniel K. Richter, "Believing That Many of the Red People Suffer Much for the Want of Food": Hunting, Agriculture, and Quaker Constructions of Indianness in the Early Republic, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 28, Folder 5)
      - Shugerman, South Carolina and the slave trade, enslaving the frontier, 1999 (Box 28, Folder 6)
      - Randy Roth, Homicide, aggression, 2011 (Box 28, Folder 7)
      - Garland, Problem of Slavery, Circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 28, Folder 8)
      - Recent papers, reviews on slavery, Jim Stewart, Ed Ayers, and Owen Williams, 2005 (Box 28, Folder 9)
      - Margaret Abruzzo manuscript, 2008 (Box 28, Folder 10)
      - USA Weekend, What Reparations Mean to America, 2002 August (Box 28, Folder 11)
      - Black Abolitionist Papers' comments, 1989 August 18 (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - Research files
    Research files include subject files on specific topics, as well as correspondence, writings, course materials and notes, and printed material pertaining to those topics.
    The research files include a small amount of unsorted mateiral pertaining to the history of the United States and the Americas. This unsorted material is filed at the end of the research files grouping.
    Some research files include student records, which are restricted as established by Yale Corporation regulations. http://web.library.yale.edu/mssa/collections/research-use-of-yaleuniversity- archives. Restricted research files are noted at the file level.
    - Black antisemitism and Nation of Islam, 1993–1995 (Box 28, Folder 13-14)
    - Isaac McCoy, 1993 (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - Indian removal, Bob Bonner materials, 1993 (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - Colonization and poverty, 1986 (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - Early British colonization scholarship, 1993 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Indian removal and comparisons, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - John G. Fee anti-slavery manual, 1848, 1986 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Slavery, colonization, and academia notes and correspondence, 1987 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Slavery, colonization, and academia notes and correspondence, student work, 1987- (Box 99, Folder 15)
      Student records are restricted until 2091 as established by Yale Corporation regulations. http://web.library.yale.edu/mssa/collections/research-use-of-yale-university-archives.
    - Material on British-American relations (post chapter 5), Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Slavery, against progress, backwardness, cross-references, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Black view, free trade and commerce, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Joseph Gurney, letter to Henry Clay, A Winter in the West Indies, 1840, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Animal Imagery in Edward Long, W. Jordan, D.B. Davis, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Eugene Genovese notes, Circa 1990-circa 1995 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Eugene Genovese notes, student work, Circa 1990-1995 (Box 99, Folder 14)
    - University of Michigan manuscript, Danforth, Bacon, Geo. Thompson, etc., ACS, 1832, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - Liberia, 2006, undated (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Russian serf emancipation, 1986-1987, undated (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Charles Darwin, British antislavery and industrial society, 2009, undated (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Jim Oakes lecture on emancipation, 2009 September 20 (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - David Eltis, Rise of African Slavery in the Americas, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 29, Folder 16)
    - Floyd Miller and Wilson J. Moses, Black Nationalism, 2001, undated (Box 29, Folder 17)
    - India, British occupation, 2007 (Box 29, Folder 18)
    - Proslavery, Bob Bonner, 2008 (Box 29, Folder 19)
    - Rob Forbes, Missouri Crisis Politics of Slavery, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 29, Folder 20)
    - Stanley L. Engerman, Weber, Protestant and capitalism, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 29, Folder 21)
    - Slave families, Brenda Stevenson, etc., 1977, 1996 (Box 29, Folder 22)
      Also includes notes and writings for the New York Review of Books.
    - Women and blacks, 1986–1989 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Early British colonization documents, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Maryland in Africa, Penelope Campbell, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Notes and correspondence regarding the Maryland State Colonization Society, 1992, undated (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Naming America and Africa, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Thomas Jefferson and Sally Hemings, 1998–1999 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Books to read or see, 2007–2008 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - History of Rome, books to get, 2008 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Drescher, Atlantic slave trade and Holocaust comparative analysis, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Idea of progress, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - Missouri crisis, new states and slavery, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - John Marshall and William Ellery Channing, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - Cincinnati trip, 2006 November (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - Research trips, 1987 (Box 30, Folder 14)
    - British travel research, 1981–1987 (Box 30, Folder 15)
    - Amistad research black press: 1847-1848, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 30, Folder 16)
    - Notes and lectures on slavery, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Notecards on sources, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 31, Folder 2-3)
    - American view, British abolitionists and others, interests, motives, et cetera, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - American view, British interesting in the United States (general), Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - American view, British hypocrisy, United States defended, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - American view, British emancipation movement, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - American view, British hypocrisy, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - American view, British churches, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - American and British responses to F.A. Cox and James Hoby, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - American view, British apprenticeship, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - American and British view of foreign interference, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 31, Folder 12)
    - American, Anglo-American perception of attempts to explain American anti-slavery to British and vice versa, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 31, Folder 13)
    - American, abolitionist defense of America against British abolitionist criticism, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 31, Folder 14)
    - American view, lessons of British West Indies emancipation successes and failures, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 31, Folder 15)
    - American view, British emancipation in India, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - American, Charles Summer to R. Cobden on British and American relations, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - American, attempts to enlist British anti-slavery support, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Abolitionist views of their role after emancipation, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - American, emancipation plans and suggestions, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - American, role of abolitionists in post-Civil War society, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - American, plan for a free labor experiment in South, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - American, free labor and African civilization, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - American, Civil War, includes voices of British opinion and role, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - American views on the Irish, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - American, miscellaneous arguments for emancipation, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - Photocopies of maps, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 32, Folder 12)
    - Reconstruction, 1990- (Box 32, Folder 13)
    - Reconstruction, student work, 1990 (Box 99, Folder 1)
    - Mind, Brain, Culture, and Consciousness, collective remembering, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - Alexander Saxton, The Rise and Fall of the White Republic, race, 1990 (Box 32, Folder 15)
    - Henri Grégoire, defense of blacks, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 32, Folder 16)
    - American Anti-Slavery Group, modern slavery, 1995 (Box 32, Folder 17)
    - George Washington, Thomas Jefferson, and Rufus King speeches, photocopies, 1994 (Box 32, Folder 18)
    - Feminism, women's rights, 2000 (Box 32, Folder 19)
    - Thomas Bender, Internationalizing of American History, New York University, 1998 (Box 32, Folder 20)
    - Steven Mintz, slavery and anti-slavery bibliography, 1996 August 21 (Box 32, Folder 21)
    - Cold War, Israel, and Arabs, 1999 (Box 32, Folder 22)
    - Affirmative action, equal outcome, 1993–1997 (Box 32, Folder 23)
    - Political correctness, absurdities, Robeson, alternative medicine, Patterson's lectures, 1998–2001 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Postmodernism, pragmatism, Richard Rorty, et cetera, 1998 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Science and God, divine in human life, 1997–2004 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Harold Brackman, Jesus and blacks, counterhistory, exodus, et cetera, 1998–1999 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Jews and slavery, Middle Ages to Caribbean, Brazil, 1994-1998 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Jews and slavery, Middle Ages to Caribbean, Brazil, student work, 1994–1998 (Box 99, Folder 2)
    - Harold Brackman, Jesus, black music, 2010 (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - Theses notes, 1998 (Box 99, Folder 3)
    - Jews and abolitionism, Civil War and racism, 1995 (Box 33, Folder 7)
    - Jews and abolitionism, Civil War and racism, student work, 1995 (Box 99, Folder 4)
    - Jews, slavery and anti-slavery, 1995 (Box 99, Folder 5)
    - British research notes, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - Rochester papers and Stanley L. Engerman festschrift, 2001 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Blacks today, legacies, Orlando Patterson, et cetera, 2007 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Reparations, apologies, 2001–2005 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - Idea of the American dream, 2008 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Summaries of books and articles on Jewish success, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Statistics on American Jewish success, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Philip D. Morgan, Michael J. Sandel, Gerald Krefetl), Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Jewish success, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Jews and blacks essay, 1996 (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Jewish liberation as a model for blacks?, 1996–1997 (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - Booker T. Washington's "Discovery of Jews", 1999 (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Slavery versus Holocaust
      - Research file, 1996 (Box 35, Folder 8)
      - Notes for Professor Davis, 1 (Box 98)
        The computer files are unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu. The request should outline the scope and purpose of the research project, why the researcher believes the material is relevant to their project, and contact information. If possible the request should also include a list of specific material of interest including collection, box, and folder numbers (or folder descriptions if folders are not numbered). The review may take several weeks.
    - Blacks and Jews, clippings, Gates; correspondence, American Historical Association, et cetera, 1991–1995 (Box 35, Folder 9)
    - American Jewish history, 1993 (Box 35, Folder 10)
    - Blacks and Jews, Davis essays, talks, correspondence, clippings, 1994–1997 (Box 35, Folder 11)
    - Notes on David Eltis writings, 1987–1993 (Box 35, Folder 12)
    - Seymour Drescher and papers, notes and controversy, 1979–1997 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Labor degraded, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Grimké sisters, G. Lerner, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - Whigs, anti-masons, nativists, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Reading, for review, 1979–1987 (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - Antislavery, 1982, undated (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - Reformer, biographical sketches, 1960, undated (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - Reform, phases, theory, 1960, undated (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - Education, pre-1860, 1978, undated (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - Law, judges, and constitution, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - Prisons and asylums, 1979, undated (Box 36, Folder 11)
    - 19th century United States, colonial and revolutionary, 1971, undated (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - Texas issue and slavery, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 36, Folder 13)
    - Anglo-America; Monroe Doctrine, expansion, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 36, Folder 14)
    - Kansas, Nebraska, and Stephen A. Douglas, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 36, Folder 15)
    - Race and racism, general, 1994–2004 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Colonization, themes, ideas, 1984-2006 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Colonization, themes, ideas, student work, 1984–2006 (Box 99, Folder 6)
      Also includes material for the Problem of Slavery in the Age of Emanicipation.
    - Slavery, Steven Mintz, email and Internet printouts, 1996 (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - IQ, race, genes, 2007, 2010 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Proslavery thought, 1967-2006 (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Proslavery thought, student work, 1967–2006 (Box 99, Folder 7)
    - Notes on C. Duncan Rice, Scottish Factor, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Notes on William Lloyd Garrison papers, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Assorted notes on slavery and reform, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - Frederick Douglass Monthly and notes from missing issue of The North Star, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - Henry Clay and colonization, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Henry Clay and colonization, student work, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 99, Folder 16)
    - Notes on Standenraus, Fredrickson, 1991 (Box 38, Folder 2)
      Also includes material on the Problem of Slavery in the Age of Emancipation.
    - Punishment, crime (sin), Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Black view, British and British emancipation, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Jean Soderlund, Quakers and Slavery, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Philo and Essenes, 2007 (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - Definitions and anthropology of slavery, 1994–2001 (Box 38, Folder 7)
    - Notes on Edward Bartlett Rugemer, Emancipation, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 38, Folder 8)
    - Black image, Menil Collection, review, and notes, 1991, undated (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - Peter Kolchin, American slavery (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - Joseph J. Ellis on Thomas Jefferson, American Sphinx, 1997, undated (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - Robert Fogel, Without Consent, 1989-1990, undated (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - Robert Fogel, Without Consent, student work, 1989-1990, undated (Box 99, Folder 8)
    - George M. Fredrickson, Inner Civil War, Walters, and antislavery appeal, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 39, Folder 5)
    - Abraham Lincoln and Harriet Beecher Stowe, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - George M. Fredrickson, white supremacy and comparative slavery, 1985, undated (Box 39, Folder 7)
    - Stanley Elkins and other files, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 39, Folder 8)
    - Concluding material, 20th century slavery, 1996–2002 (Box 39, Folder 9)
    - Assorted notes and New York Review of Books material, 1994–1996 (Box 39, Folder 10)
    - Richard Wightman Fox biography of Reinhold Niebuhr, 1986, undated (Box 39, Folder 11)
      Also includes material for the New York Review of Books.
    - British West Indies emancipation results from 1845 onward, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 39, Folder 12)
    - James Madison on slavery, 1995, undated (Box 39, Folder 13)
    - Notes on slavery and Winthrop Jordan, Tumult and Silence, 1993–1994 (Box 39, Folder 14)
    - Lawrence Jacob Friedman, Gregarious Saints, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 39, Folder 15)
    - Notes on Robert Sean Wilentz and labor radicals, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 39, Folder 16)
    - Joel Williamson, Crucible of Race, 1985, undated (Box 39, Folder 17)
    - Stanley Elkins, Richard King, and St. Petersburg, Florida, 2000 (Box 39, Folder 18)
    - Notes on Winthrop Jordan, White over Black, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 39, Folder 19)
    - Notes on books on slavery, 1994–2000 (Box 39, Folder 20)
    - Slavery in a capitalist world, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 39, Folder 21)
      Also includes course lecture notes.
    - Prudence Crandall, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - Notes JAH manuscript, Abolitionists versus capitalists, 2004, undated (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - Dick Brodhead, American literature and slavery, 1996 (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - George Fitzhugh to Gerrit Smith, 1996 (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - David Northrup, Atlantic slave trade, Circa 1960s-circa 2010 (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - Edmund Morgan, American slavery, American freedom, 1995, undated (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - Edmund Morgan, American slavery, American freedom, student work, 1995, undated (Box 99, Folder 9)
    - Slavery and debt and death paper, 2010 (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - Notes, on Joe Wilkins and M. Sinha, Circa 1990s-circa 2010 (Box 40, Folder 8)
    - Robert Fogel, The Slavery Debates, 2001–2002 (Box 40, Folder 9)
    - John Thornton and Patrick Manning, Circa 1990s-circa 2010 (Box 40, Folder 10)
    - Right of research controversy, Circa 1990s-circa 2010 (Box 40, Folder 11)
    - Thomas Bacon, Circa 1990s-circa 2010 (Box 40, Folder 12)
    - Kansas, Free soil versus free Blacks, Circa 1990s-circa 2010 (Box 40, Folder 13)
    - Kansas, Issue, Circa 1990s-circa 2010 (Box 40, Folder 14)
    - Illinois legislature, 1824 convention controversy, Circa 1990s-circa 2010 (Box 40, Folder 15)
    - Anti-abolitionist views, gradualists and view of Vermont Chronicle, Circa 1990s-circa 2010 (Box 40, Folder 16)
    - American, Southern view, general, Circa 1990s-circa 2010 (Box 40, Folder 17)
    - Fugitive Slave Law, makes free North accomplice of slavery as a form of dominion, Circa 1990s-circa 2010 (Box 40, Folder 18)
    - Petition versus Fugitive Slave Law, Circa 1990s-circa 2010 (Box 40, Folder 19)
    - Fugitive slaves, drama, Circa 1990s-circa 2010 (Box 40, Folder 20)